<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Captain Charles Newy's case impartially laid open, or, A true    and full narrative of the clandestine proceedings aginst [sic] him as it was hatched, contrived, and maliciously carried on by Mrs. Margaret  Newey, widdow.</title>
            <author>Newey, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42213</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24421544</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24421544</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109696</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53097)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109696)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1708:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Captain Charles Newy's case impartially laid open, or, A true    and full narrative of the clandestine proceedings aginst [sic] him as it was hatched, contrived, and maliciously carried on by Mrs. Margaret  Newey, widdow.</title>
                  <author>Newey, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 14: Newey.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Newey, Charles.</term>
               <term>Newey, Margaret.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109696:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Captain Charles Newy's CASE, Impartially Laid Open:</p>
            <p>Or, a True and Full NARATIVE OF THE Clandeſtine Proceedings aginſt Him, As it was Hatched, Contrived, and Maliciouſly Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by <hi>Mrs. Margaret Newey, Widdow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author in the Year, 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:109696:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109696:2"/>
            <head>Captain Charles Newey's CASE, Impartially Laid Open.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>CANDID READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Should be wanting to my ſelf, to you, and indeed to the Publick, ſhould I not at this time of Day make known to the World, how Strangely and Maliciouſly I have been Wronged and Traduced, by the wild and cauſeleſs Malice of an Inhuman, I had almoſt ſaid Barbarous Siſter. And tho it is a very dificult Matter for me to expreſs my Self, in ſuch words as ſhall undeceive the World, and thorowly Convince the Vulgar, with the truth of my Innocence (eſpecially conſidering we Live, in an Age wherein Men have got the trick of Troop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after one another in Flocks like <hi>Sheep,</hi> they follow the Bell, and if the foremoſt leap the Bridge, the reſt Drowns for Company) yet I hope my Reader will give me leave to Vindicate my Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie; tho' I am told I might with more Safety have Ventured my Carcaſs with <hi>Dannel</hi> in the <hi>Lyon's-Denn,</hi> than to have reſiſted the Torrent that was rais'd againſt me; Yet even as I am not oblig'd to Suffer all the Dirt that can be raked out of the <hi>Kennells,</hi> and <hi>Common-Shoars,</hi> to be Plaſtered on my Face, without Lifting up a Hand to wipe it off, even ſo I ought not to ſuffer this Harmony of Lyes and Defamation to paſs Currant, without either Contradiction or Controul: Conſcience muſt be then fallen a Sleep and Truth Struck Dumb: I hope I ſhall not be thought to do in this, as ſome do by Cutting the Throat of their own <hi>Religion</hi> by Contending for it; be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing very Senſible that there goes more than <hi>Greek,</hi> or <hi>Latin</hi> to the making of a wiſe Man. But to proceed.</p>
            <p>I ſhall lay before your View, in the firſt place the Commitment it ſelf, in the ſecond, ſhall ſo expatiat my ſelf on each particular, as I hope will fully Satisfy any Impartial Reader with the Truth of my Innocencie.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <head>Here is the Committment it ſelf, by Vertue of which I was Committed to <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>MIDDLESEX,</opener>
                        <p>Receive into your Cuſtody the Body of <hi>Charles Newey</hi> Gent. herewith ſent you, he having Confeſſed before me on his Examination, that he is Lawfully Marryed to one <hi>Barbara Ferrour;</hi> And Oath having been made before me by <hi>Margaret Newey</hi> Widdow, that ſhe hath ſeveral times heard the ſaid <hi>Charles Newey</hi> acknowledge, that he was Lawfully Marryed to one <hi>Hannah Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge;</hi> And that both the ſaid <hi>Barbara</hi> and <hi>Hannah</hi> are ſtill Living: The ſaid <hi>Margaret Newey</hi> having likewiſe made Oath before me, that ſhe has heard the ſaid <hi>Charles Newy</hi> Confeſs and Acknowledge and is ſure, that in ſome Short time after the Deceaſe of the late Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> he Hung the Gallows with Mourning for the ſaid Queen: He ſtanding likewiſe Charg'd before me upon the Oath of <hi>Ralph Armfield</hi> Headborrough, for drawing his Sword, and preſenting a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol at him and his Aſſiſtants, and Beating him in the Execution of his Office; you are therefore hereby required, him ſafe to keep, untill he ſhall be Diſcharged by due courſe of Law, And for ſo doing this ſhall be your Warrant,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given under my Hand and Seal, <date>the 18th day of <hi>November</hi> Anno Domini, 1699.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>S. Lovell</hi> Recorder.</signed>
                           <hi>Copia Vera.</hi>
                        </closer>
                        <trailer>To the Keeper of His Majeſty's Goal of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                        </trailer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But before I proceed to handle each particular Branch Specifyed in this Committment, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it convenient to acquaint my Reader with the Nature of my firſt Tryal, which will clear up the whole matter.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt and greateſt Crime then, which I was accuſed of, and the only cauſe of my being found guilty of the reſt, was for endeavouring, as the Wittneſſes againſt me alleadg'd, to take away my Brother's Life, which indeed the World has ſome reaſon to believe, tho' it was never my Intentions, neither did it ever enter into my Thoughts.</p>
            <p>He was extream week, and ſolely Govern'd by his Wife, who found him inclind to leave his Brother's all he had but only her Thirds. To prevent which ſhe uſed all the Stratagems
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109696:3"/>ſhe could invent, to create a Difference, purely to accompliſh her deſignes; which ſhe thoro'ly did, by telling him that the Captains Lady, who is of an Unſpotted Reputation had ſtolen his Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Tankard, as ſhe came to Viſit her, which can be aſſerted by Mr. <hi>Ferrour</hi> and his Wife, at the <hi>Tebacce-Rowl</hi> in <hi>Newgate-market,</hi> they having had it from my ſaid Brothers own Mouth. My Brother likewiſe by his Wives Perſwaſions, went to one Mr. <hi>Claviſes,</hi> a <hi>Dutch School-master</hi> in the <hi>Pall-Mell,</hi> where I had Lodg'd from time to time for Two Years; and there reported all that Hell and Malice could invent againſt me, telling the People of the Houſe, (who till then entertain'd a good Opinion of me) <hi>that I deſign'd to fling their Goods out at the Windows, and Pawn them, as I had done the pretended Stolen Tankard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This he did ſeveral times when I was from Home, and ſeeing I took no Notice of it; He came one <hi>Sunday</hi> at Night, with Conſtables, having before Sir <hi>Charles Leigh</hi> Swore the Peace againſt me, and diſgrac'd me all he could amongſt the Neighbours, ſhowing his Warrant and repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what had been Invented by his Wife, who at that time, the Devil had not aſſured, or had it entered into her thoughts that I Hung the Gallows in Mourning. There was no living for me in <hi>England,</hi> if my Brothers ill Uſage continued: I writ to him to forbear, and told him what his Wife aim'd at: Which Letters were produc'd againſt me in Court. But finding that there was no being quiet, or preventing to be believ'd what was told, and is ſince Creditted by the whole Town, not only in their Shop, but every Body they met or knew, and that my Prayers were of no uſe, I was adviſed by ſome as unthinking as my ſelf, to proſecute my ſaid Brother, but not to that degree, as to take away his Life, for the thing for which he was Indicted, was only a breach of Truſt, and purely done to induce him to let me alone.</p>
            <p>I left ſeveral Trunks which contained what I had, at my ſaid Brothers Houſe, when I went to <hi>Norfolk,</hi> but at my return found them all broken open in their Cuſtody, ſome they return'd me by fair means. The grand Jury found the Bill and I had a ſearch Warrant, which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd ſerving, in hopes he would forbear ſpeaking Ill of me; ſome of the aforementioned things were ſound in their Houſe, as the Two Conſtables <hi>viz.</hi> one Mr. <hi>Phips</hi> who Lives at the <hi>Kings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> near <hi>Holbourn Bars</hi> can juſtifie, as well as the other.</p>
            <p>But it is not denyed that my Brother was Sick of the Foul Diſtemper, under which he, languiſh'd for Two or Three Years together, he was Bail'd and did not Die in <hi>Newgate,</hi> as was reported, but at his own Houſe. His Wife together with thoſe of her party perſwaded him to make uſe of his Credit, and what he had to ruine me, which prevented his coming to any A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with me; And I am ſure the World can't but believe, if they will but lay prjudice aſide, that it was my Intereſt, rather to looſe, what I had realy loſt out of my Trunks, or lent him out of my Pocket, than what he promiſed to leave me, Nay one Day ſhewed me in a Will he made. But finding my Brother grow worſe and more averſe to what I could offer to be Friends by others, not being permitted by my Siſter's means to ſpeak to him and inſtead of it threatened to be ruin'd by Actions of Scandal, and forfeiture of my Recognizance if. I did not appear at the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> which I did, to make an appologie for my raſhneſs, and to leave it to them and be diſcharged, as my Counſel in that caſe cannot deny I knew he was in no danger, having a good reputation and giving 2000 <hi>l.</hi> Bail: And am ſince Satisfied that it was not him but my Siſter that broke open my Trunks.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Tyſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Watſon,</hi> and his Wife, were all in Court to juſtifie my being forward and willing, to put a ſtop to all proceedings, as a certain ſign of my Brother's Innocency: The Tryal was from time to time deferr'd and put off by my Sick Brother's deſire, who was brought thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his Wives perſwaſion, he having firſt made a Will and left her all, tho' a Dying, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, in hopes by that means ſhe might get rid of him, for there was poſitively no occaſion for his coming after giving Bail. By Death his Wife got her ends, that is, rid of a Sick Husband: That could not ſatisfy her, and what he had, to preſerve which ſhe muſt have her Husbands Brothers Blood, and gain as many as ſhe could of her Neighbours, and others to her party, by telling Scandalous and ſuppoſed Crimes againſt me, its believed by them, and is repeated by her, to every Creature that came or comes into her Shop, or is known by her, ſometimes crying, but always ſuiting her Diſcourſe and Actions ſo, as to gain Credit by all. But to come to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>My Brother leaving me but a Shilling, tho' he owed me 105 Guineas and ought to have given me ſhare of what my Father left: Whereupon I cited my ſaid Siſter into <hi>Doctors-Commons</hi> Court knowing her to be the worſt of Creatures; I offered her (by Mrs. <hi>Tyſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wattſon,</hi> and others) to put my prtenſions upon her, to Two or more indifferent Perſons which ſhe refuſed: Being then well Satisfied that ſhe muſt pay me, and return what elſe was my due.</p>
            <p>Now that my Reader may be thoro'ly convinced that my ſaid Brother did realy, and juſtly, owe me 105 Guineas, and that he gave me his Note for them, appears thus.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="promissory_note">
                        <p>I promiſe to pay my Brother <hi>Charles Newey</hi> the Summ of 105 Guineas, or procure him a Hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Coach Licence in 3 Days.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Wittneſs my Hand <date>the 5th. Day of <hi>March</hi> 1698/9.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Witneſſed by <hi>John Ball.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>This <hi>John Ball</hi> ſerv'd me about Two Years, and went to live above 100 Miles off, but where abouts I know not, by which means I could not produce him in Court to prove my Brothers Hand, and his ſeeing me pay down the Guineas as aforeſaid.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:109696:3"/>
            <p>But this Note was not denyed by my Brother or his Wife when Arreſted, tho' he ſometimes ſaid he laid out more than that came to, for me when I was Young; and at other times ſaid that he had repai'd the Summ, but had forgot to take up his Note, which ſome of his Neighbours heard. This Note has been ſhewed to a Hundred that dealt with my Brother for ſome Years, who all declare it to be his Hand: It has been compared with that in <hi>Doctors-Commons,</hi> and my Brother that is living knows it to be his Hand. Now if this Note was realy my ſaid Brothers, and that he had paid it as my Siſter pleads, how can it be proved forgery? or how can it be proved a Cheat, otherwiſe then by proving that he realy paid it.</p>
            <p>I admire that thoſe who were told by my Brother, or his Wife, that I had lent them ſuch a Summ, but that they had return'd it can ſee, or ſuffer my kind Siſter, without an abhorrence of her Swearing, that there was no ſuch Summ ever lent her Husband, and that too, after her owning it to ſeveral: And that the Letters I produced under her Husband's Hand was not of his Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tho' known to be his by every one but her, whoſe Intereſt it was not to own them: But to prove the matter a little more fully.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hubbards</hi> Niece tho' but Young, and not us'd to appear in places of Judicature, had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in Writing before, what ſhe knew concerning it, and in Court what was permitted her, tho' to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>This is what ſhe is ready to Sweare before any Magiſtrate. <hi>Sarah Laply</hi> of the Pariſh of St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s in the Fields Spinſter, maketh Oath,</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <p>That upon <hi>Sunday</hi> the 5th of March, 1698/9 Captain <hi>Charles Newey</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Newey</hi> Glover, came to this Deponants Uncles Houſe about Six a Clock in the Evening, this Deponant letting them in, and that whilſt this Deponant went to light the Fire, when ſhe came again into the Room ſhe ſaw the ſaid Captain <hi>Newey,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>John Newey</hi> count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Table in the Dining Room a parcel of Guineas, which as this Deponant doth gueſs might be above <hi>100:</hi> Whereupon the ſaid Captain <hi>Newey</hi> called this Deponant and asked her whether ſhe could Write, this Deponant replyed ſhe could not, whereupon he ſaid, ſhe muſt bear Wittneſs and take notice that he lent the ſaid <hi>John Newey 105</hi> Guineas, the ſaid <hi>John Newey</hi> at the ſame time bidding this Deponant remember that he was to repay the ſaid <hi> 105</hi> Guineas to Capt. <hi>Charles Newey</hi> in Three Days, or to procure him the ſaid Capt. <hi>Newey</hi> a <hi>Hackney</hi> Coach Licence, Capt. <hi>Newey</hi>'s Man at the ſame time ſetting his Hand to a Note as Wittneſs to the ſame.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>Witneſſed by <hi>John Ball.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>The Mark of <hi>Sarah</hi> A <hi>Laply.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>By all which 'tis Evident to the World, that my ſaid Brother Mr. <hi>John Newey</hi> did borrow from me 105 Guineas, which he in his Life time never repaid. And the progreſs I made in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering from my Siſter in Law what was juſtly my own, has induced her as is ſuppoſed and believed, to procure one <hi>Edward Jones</hi> alias <hi>Ambrell,</hi> alias <hi>Clement,</hi> to come to me as I was giving orders to my Proctor againſt her, as Mr. <hi>Barret</hi> of <hi>Doctors-Commons</hi> Swore in Court, and does ſtill declare. <hi>Jones</hi> told me, <hi>that he knew enough to Ruin Mrs.</hi> Newey <hi>and</hi> Hannah Goodridge <hi>to prevent their doing me any harm,</hi> and at the ſame time affirmed this with ſuch a plauſible Story, that he would have gained belief of any one, he came often to me as was, and can be proved, and told me that what he ſaid was true; which agreed with what I knew, and had been told me by my Brother and one <hi>Hanwel</hi> a notorious Coyner lately Executed, who had Sworn Coyning againſt my Brother. But for me, who fetcht him out of the <hi>Savoy</hi> to the hazard of my Life, and made him deny that, and return what Money he had got to purſue that Trade, which was not denyed by my Brother before his Neighbours, or diſown'd now by my Enemies, tho' not in full: This with my being told that my Siſter deſign'd to charge me with ſome ſuch thing induced me to go with the aforeſaid <hi>Jones</hi> before Juſtice <hi>Ellis,</hi> not as a Proſecutor, which I proteſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, but to clear my ſelf of what ſhe might lay Maliciouſly to my Charge.</p>
            <p>In fine, ſhe was admitted to Bail, and the ſaid <hi>Jones</hi> for want of Sureties was Committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> who if he had been ſuborned by me, or any other Perſon would then have declar'd it, purely that he might not have gone to Priſon; In which he was a Month before he could be wrought upon by my Enemies, as he himſelf acknowledged, to Swear <hi>that I was to give him</hi> 10 <hi>Guineas to Swear againſt my Siſter, and the aforeſaid Hannah Goodridge;</hi> which he the ſooner did, becauſe that his intended Eſcape out of Priſon was diſcovered; and he for the ſame put into the Hole, with Notice that I was a Priſoner in the <hi>Preſs-Yard,</hi> and that I would certainly be Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that he had no way to ſave his Life, but by making himſelf an Evidence againſt me, which Honeſt Mr <hi>Allen</hi> the famous <hi>Sub-Ordinary</hi> of <hi>Newgate</hi> perſwaded him to, telling him, <hi>that he with the reſt of the World believed him Perjured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Mrs. <hi>Newey</hi> was a good Woman and to be his Wife, and if he would Write a diſcovery to the Lord <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Recorder</hi> he would carry it; which Office my Reader will find, Honeſt Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> did: But neither that, or any thing elſe would the ſaid <hi>Allen</hi> do without a Bribe.</p>
            <p>But that you may be more particularly acquainted with his Honeſty and the Tranſactions of his Life, I only deſire all Mankind to ſatisfy themſelves how this pretended <hi>Prieſt</hi> behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the <hi>Colledge</hi> of <hi>Dublin</hi> and how he left it? how he came to abandon that Kingdom? and whether he has not a Wife there; how he came to fly into <hi>Italy,</hi> and what Religion he there
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109696:4"/>profeſſed, ſeeing he was forced there to Live upon the Charity of others? as may appear by his Poverty before he became the <hi>Ordinary</hi> of <hi>Newgate,</hi> and what Trickes he play'd before he had it for a Maintenance? What Cheats he hath from time to time fixed on the poor Priſoners of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate:</hi> But to conclude, with that which is moſt Notorious, the ſaid <hi>Allen</hi> went to one Capt. <hi>Riggby,</hi> now a Priſoner in the <hi>Preſs-Yard</hi> and deſired him to put into his Hands what Mony he deſign'd to leave the Poor, (he the ſaid Capt. <hi>Riggby</hi> being at that time very Sick) replyed, <hi>that he had already diſpos'd of his Charity to the Poor of the Pariſh;</hi> but ſeeing he was diſappointed that way, he Begg'd the ſaid Captains Morning Gown, conſidering it better to play at a ſmall Game than ſtand out.</p>
            <p>But to let my Reader know, what a famous Pillar of the Church of <hi>England</hi> Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> is; pray ſatisfy your ſelf, whether he did not inform on Mr. <hi>Tooley</hi> (who was afterwards Hang'd in Chains on <hi>Finchley-Common</hi> for ſome notorious Crime) whether he did not, (I ſay) inform the ſaid <hi>Tooley,</hi> and Preach'd the ſame Doctrin in his Pulpit, to the Priſoners of <hi>Newgate,</hi> on the 21 of <hi>April</hi> Laſt, that it would not be asked them in another World what Religion they profeſſed here, but what good they had done? now if this famous Doctors Opinion be True, as certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is not, then it is no matter of what Religion, or Profeſſion ſo ever a Man be of: And if ſo, then farewel the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which by his concluſion is no better then the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Theſe with many other Crimes of the like nature, the ſaid <hi>Allen</hi> is daily Guilty of: But for my part, I judge him not worth my Trouble, ſo leave him to the reſult of better Penns to diſplay him in his own Colours, and return to proſecute my former matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jones</hi> whom before I gave you ſome account of, had Linnen and 10 <hi>s.</hi> at a time ſent him, which can be proved, before he could be brought to Unſwear what he had already Sworn, which if they would have produced in Court, would have been the cleareſt Evidence for me. But I could not get what he unſwore before Juſtice <hi>Ellis</hi> at the <hi>Dog Tavern,</hi> and charg'd me with, till of late; and then not intire.</p>
            <p>Oh! that I were but capable of comparing Evidences, times, place, and Perſons; I ſhould then find ſuch a Latitude for Exceptions, Diſtinctions, Evaſions, and Interpretations, as authentickly would ſerve to clear up the whole matter, ſo much allowance for not knowing what an Oath mean'd, and pretext of ſurpriſes, ſlips of Memory, and upon the whole, ſo ſtrong a prepoſſeſſion in favour of my Enemies, and againſt every thing that could be ſaid for me: My Proſecutors would have been believed without opening their Mouths, ſpecially in a time when Oathes are grown as cheap as ſtinking <hi>Mackarel,</hi> and the common People as ready to give Credit to falſe reports, as Tinder is to take Fire at the leaſt Spark. There can be little ſaid to Invallidate a poſitive Oath for the King; the matter will be this, That True or Falſe, Credible or Incredible, Poſſible or Impoſſible, it comes all to one point. But I hope it will appear that my Siſter's Malice is to me, as if ſo many Rogues in Red-coates ſhould Robb the Kings <hi>Chappel,</hi> and cry the Guards did it: The Fact, with which I am charg'd, lyes all open to every individual Perſon, done or not done is the queſtion, how then can any man believe that I endeavoured to Hang my Brother, when the thing for which he was Indicted was but a breach of truſt? or how can any Man believe that I gave 10 Guineas to a Villain that never was maſter of one, or that could not be truſted to fetch ſix penney worth of <hi>Turnips</hi> by any, but a Mad Man; and all this to prove a thing of which I wanted no proof, having Witneſſes ſufficient for any C— that had not reſolv'd upon my Ruin, or how can any man disbelieve what has been falſly reported of me, without the utmoſt abhorrence of the practiſes and indeed of the practiſers too, If found at laſt to be moſt notoriouſly Falſe; or that their monſtrous Snake in the Graſs ſhould be found but a Glow-worm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward Jones</hi> own'd in Court that he had perjur'd himſelf before Sr. <hi>Robert Jefferies,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Ambrell</hi> tho' his Name was <hi>Clement,</hi> and that he was brib'd and not only promis'd his Liberty as a reward of his Perjury, but a ſumm of Money appears in ſome Meaſure to be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him, likewiſe as by his own Letter to me may more fully appear.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Here is the Copy of the Letter it ſelf.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honoured Sr.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Intend to Morrow to ſend a Letter to the Warden of the <hi>Mint,</hi> to acquaint him how by under hand dealings they would have me to unſay what I have already ſaid: When it is writ I will convey it to you, that you with your Friends may give your judgment upon it, and pray in the mean time believe no flying Stories of me, for as I have ever been, am, and ſhall always be.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From the Hole <date>
                           <hi>November</hi> 19. 1699.</date> 
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Honoured Sr. Your moſt Humble Servant <hi>Edward Jones.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>Directed to Capt. <hi>Newey</hi> in the <hi>Preſs-Yard.</hi>
                  </trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter was produced in Court, and not diſown'd by him, but the <hi>Ordinary</hi> who is the worſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> pretended in Court, that he went by chance to exhort the Priſoners before their Tryals, which he never did before nor ſince, but was made uſe of as a Tool by my Siſter and others to accompliſh my Ruin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jones</hi> at firſt denied that ever I ſet him on to Swear what he Swore: Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> told the Court
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109696:4"/>
               <hi>that he had Converted</hi> Jones, <hi>and made him Senſible of an Oath which he pretended he knew not what it meant, and therefore asked ſeveral times Pardon of God and the Court for having Forſworn himſelf,</hi> which the Court was pleas'd to do, in conſideration of the good Service he did againſt me, who am now found to be the worſt of Men for asking for 105 Guineas, which I realy lent, or what elſe was my due.</p>
            <p>When I ſent to <hi>Jones</hi> to know if he was ſuch a Rogue as I was inform'd he was, in deſigning to Forſwear himſelf againſt me, he denied it with all the Oathes he was Maſter of; and ſent me this Paper Witneſſed by three Perſons, which convinc'd me that what I was told was falſe, and cauſed me to be unprepar'd for my Tryal.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Here is the Paper it ſelf ſent me by <hi>Jones.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I do think my ſelf Oblig'd by all that's ſacred, to declare to all the World out of my own free Will and Gonſent without any force, or compulſion, or any reward, or promiſe of any; that <hi>Charles Newey</hi> Eſq never did nor any other Perſon at any time deſire, or ask me to be an Evidence againſt Mrs. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet Newey,</hi> or any other Perſon upon any account whatſoever, but what I did was for the good of the Government, and for fear of being brought into Trouble hereafter, and out of no other conſideration:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>In Witneſs of the Truth I have hereunto ſet my Hand <date>the 25th <hi>Day of</hi> October 1699.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Edward Jones.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <head>Witneſſed by,</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Philemon Wike.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Powell.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The mark † of <hi>William Guy.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This <hi>Jones</hi> alias <hi>Ambrell,</hi> alias <hi>Clement,</hi> is a known Evidence in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> a Perjur'd one in Mr. <hi>Cooper</hi>'s Tryal, ſo could not be Ignorant of an Oath, for what he Swears in the ſaid Tryal was not thought Reaſonable to be believed, for Dr. <hi>Garth</hi> who is a Senſible and worthy Perſon and who will I hope excuſe this; told the Court <hi>they had Reaſon to ſuſpect the pretended Seamans Evidence, that Three or Four Score-pounds of</hi> Iron, <hi>ſhould be allowed to ſink every Dead Body, whereas Six, or Seven will do as well;</hi> neither can the World with him believe the Comiſſioners of the Navy Guilty of ſo much Ill Husbandry; but more at length will be found in <hi>pag.</hi> 31. of Mr. <hi>Coopers</hi> Tryal for the ſuppoſed Murther of Mrs. <hi>Stout.</hi> This <hi>Jones</hi> Swore that <hi>he was made Drank the Night before by me, to Engage him the more eaſily to Forſwear himſelf, that he did not know well what he did:</hi> When before Juſtice <hi>Ellis;</hi> that he was made Drunk by me, or any other, was not proved, nor in what Tavern. But put caſe he was Drunk as he pretends; pray how came it about that Juſtice <hi>Ellis</hi> did not perceive it? If he did, why did he adminiſter an Oath to a Drunken Man, or act as he did? and tho' <hi>Jones</hi> deſerves to be Encouraged againſt me, yet why in Forſwearing himſelf before Sr. <hi>Robert Jefferies,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Ambrell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deſire that half the Priſoners may be asked what a wicked Villain this <hi>Jones</hi> was, and how he behav'd himſelf whilſt in <hi>Newgate.</hi> He was found to have committed <hi>Sodomy</hi> with one <hi>Barnes,</hi> who own'd it whilſt in the Goal: It no ſooner came to my Ears, but my Siſter and honeſt Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> who had all along a Hand in my Proſecution, got him out, for fear I ſhould Proſecute him, and ſo their deſigns be diſcovered, he was brought to my Siſter's Houſe, who ſent for her Neighbours, and there made him ſay what ſhe thought fit, they paid his Fees, and gave him Mony as can be proved, with ſeveral other Tricks, too long to be incerted here.</p>
            <p>As to my being Married to Two Wives is what no Creature (who will lay aſide prejudice and impartially weigh the whole matter) can believe: But that my Reader may be acquainted with the circumſtances of the whole, I will lay open the occaſion of my firſt acquaintance with the ſaid <hi>Hannah Goodridge,</hi> mentioned in the firſt paragraph of my committment, and fixt on me as a lawful Wife.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Hannah Goodridge</hi> was a Servant where I Lodg'd, ſhe pretending to help me to a Fortune of 10000 <hi>l.</hi> by the Intereſt ſhe had in a young Lady where ſhe lived, which induced me to be more kind to her than otherwiſe I ſhould have been, and ſhe for want of it, ſo much my Enemie. I went to <hi>Drayton</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire</hi> where I was Born, the firſt and only time ſince my being in <hi>England,</hi> in my return near <hi>Northampton,</hi> I found her at her Aunts, ready to carry on the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Intrigue, which miſcarring, I left her and came for <hi>London,</hi> where ſhe followed me, and took me before one Juſtice <hi>Eaton,</hi> for a Baſtard Child, and for cheating her of a Suite of Cloathes which ſhe pretended to have paſſed her Word to the Taylor for, tho' I paid him, this is that which Mr. <hi>Watſon</hi> now Clerk to Juſtice <hi>Ireton</hi> knows to be true, but to prove that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her Mother nor any of her Relations in the Country, thought her Married to me, or any other, tho' her Siſter Swore in Court, ſhe believed ſhe was to me.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="promissory_note">
                        <head>Be pleas'd to View the enſuing Note.</head>
                        <p>Dear Siſter Boughton, deliver into the Hands of my Daughter <hi>Hannah Goodridge</hi> the Tenn Pounds Tenn Shillings you have of mine, and this ſhall be your diſcharge and acquittance;</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>whereunto I have ſet my Hand, <date>the <hi>16th</hi> Day of <hi>November 1695.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>M Goodridge.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Witneſſed by <hi>Ann Pratt.</hi> And <hi>Mary Pratt.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>By all which its Evident that no Creature who knows me or her can believe, that I was ever Married to her, I ſay no Mortal can beleve it, and keep his Reaſon. Now that there muſt be ſome Reaſon to induce me to this pretended Marriage is not to be doubted; Youth it was not, for ſhe is 50, nor Beauty for there is nothing Uglier, nor for any thing ſhe could have, for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109696:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:109696:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:109696:6"/>that as ſhe and her party own'd in Court, was but a few <hi>Kettles, Diſhes,</hi> and the like: Family there is no likelihood it ſhould be for; ſhe being but a Servant Maid. Now what muſt I have been to have Married ſuch a Creature; or if Married to more than one, why not to a 1000, or till I had got a Fortune. The Puniſhment would have been the ſame. That I never wanted Cloathes, is ſo known by every one that knew me, that I need not ſay the Contrary, that I might have had a better, is allowed me by my cruel Enemies: That there ſhould be no Body at this Sham-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; but this Fellow, and ſhe ſo eaſily Impoſed upon, being 50. and a <hi>Jilt</hi> about Town, is ſome what ſtrange: And that it ſhould be done in a Tavern, and the only one in <hi>Somerſet-Houſe,</hi> and in <hi>Latin,</hi> which I am known to underſtand ſomething of: Therefore could not be Impos'd upon unleſs in a Dream. There was no Licence taken out, nor no other proof, than this perjur'd Wretch, who indeed I knew in <hi>France</hi> and often Relieved here, but being too much importun'd by him I beat him as he Swore in Court, as appears by his own Letter to me which is as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Capt. Newey,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I deſire you to leave in the Coffee Man's Hands <hi>10</hi> s. which I paid the <hi>Surgeon,</hi> for the Cure of my Thumb and Head; he demanded Twenty, but I have paid no more, and I ſcorn to ask you more then I have paid, it was a long time in the Cure, during which time I could not Write, I loſt the uſe of my Eye and 'tis the Opinion of the <hi>Surgeon</hi> and others, that it will never return to 'its former ſhape. The Pain and Miſery I have indured with it makes me at leaſt demand this, and if you will be as Civil as you have promiſed, you will certainly do it: I expect your anſwer, or the thing done, either of which ſhall ſatisfy</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>September</hi> the 18th 1699.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Sr.</salute>
                     <signed>Your moſt Humble Servant <hi>Phillip Hollingworth.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>So far was I from thinking it lay in his power to do me the leaſt Harm, that you ſee by his own acknowledgment, that I did realy Beat him, which any Creature may conclude I would not have done, had I judg'd it in his power to have done me a Miſchief, but I realy believe what he and <hi>Goodridge</hi> at firſt did, was only to extort Mony from me as he owns in his Affidavit, which is demonſtration ſufficient of his Villany and my Innocency, with his being ſet on by my Siſter. This Fellow did of his own free will and conſent go to Mr. <hi>Hatchers</hi> (who's of an unſpoted Reputation) at his Chambers in <hi>Lincolns-Inn</hi> as was Sworn in Court and deſir'd the ſaid <hi>Hatcher</hi> to draw up an Affidavit, which he did, keeping by him the Draught which <hi>Holl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingworth</hi> at firſt drew: Which the ſaid <hi>Hatcher</hi> produced in Court, together with the Original Affidavit which he there made Oath of; And likewiſe that <hi>Hollingworth</hi> had been ſeveral times at his Chambers without me, importuning him to draw the ſaid Affidavit, and to perſwade me that he never ſaid he ever Married me, or knew any thing of the matter. Here is a true Copy of the Affidavit he made in <hi>Chancery.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="affidavit">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Phillip Hollingworth</hi> Clerk Aged <hi>47</hi> Years, maketh Oath, that he this Deponant never Married Capt. <hi>Charles Newey</hi> to <hi>Hannah Goodridge</hi> Spinſter, or to any other Woman whatſoever: But this Deponant Confeſſeth it to be true, that he complied with the Malice and ill Intentions of the ſaid <hi>Hannah Goodridge</hi> to Proſecute the ſaid <hi>Charles Newey,</hi> in Relation to the ſaid pretended Marriage in order to obtain, or extort from him the ſaid Capt. <hi>Newey,</hi> a Maintenance or Proviſion for the ſaid <hi>Hannah,</hi> as his pretended Wife.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Jurat 10 die Martij 1699.</date> Coram me Rog Meridith.</dateline>
                           <signed>Phillip Hollingworth.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="affidavit">
                        <head>Here is a Copy of another Affidavit before Judge <hi>Turton.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Elizabeth Chattleton</hi> maketh Oath, that ſhe this Deponant was on the 8th Inſtant ſent for to one Dr. <hi>Hollingworth</hi>'s, but not being in the way did not go to him till next morning, who then asked this Deponant if ſhe would do him the kindneſs as to go to one Capt. <hi>Newey</hi> in the <hi>Preſs-Yard,</hi> and to aſſure the Capt. from the ſaid <hi>Hollingworth,</hi> that if the Capt. or his Friends would give the ſaid <hi>Holl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingworth</hi> Five Guineas, he the ſaid <hi>Hollingworth</hi> would give any Security in Writing, or any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways that the Capt. or his Friends ſhould deſire, that he the ſaid <hi>Hollingworth</hi> would not appear againſt the Capt. at the <hi>Old-Baily</hi> and that he knew nothing of any Marriage between the Capt. and <hi>Hannah Goodridge,</hi> and that he would go to <hi>Oxford,</hi> or any other place he ſhould appoint, for he would not wrong his Conſcience in taking a falſe Oath, for he was afraid that Mrs. <hi>Newey,</hi> Siſter to the Capt. or Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> would force him to take away the Captain's Life, if he did not go out of Town which the Dr. had no Mony to do, for he was at that time very Poor. That the ſaid <hi>Hollingworth</hi> did then uſe to this Deponant all the Arguments poſſible for this Deponant to repeat to the Capt. that he might be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to ſend him <hi>5</hi> Guineas; and to tell the Capt. that he had a great many Enemies and that every thing would be believed by the Court and Jury to the Captains prejudice. All which this Deponant did do, finding the Capt. Sick in his Chamber, who when he heard what I had to ſay from <hi>Hollingworth,</hi> he call'd him perjur'd Rogue, and ſaid he would give him no Mony and told this Deponant ſhe ought to be taken up for coming to him. And further this Deponant declareth it to be true, that when ſhe came back to the Dr. whom this Deponant hath known for ſeveral Years, and told him the Captains Anſwer, he ſaid G—d D—n him, he would certainly Hang the Rogue, and he ſhould repent it.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Jurat 15 die <hi>Jan.</hi> 1699.</date> Coram <hi>Jo. Turton.</hi>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>The Mark of <hi>Eliz. E Chattleton.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:109696:6"/>
            <p>The Court would not ſuffer this Affidavit to be Read, or others I have to the ſame Effect, alledging that no Affidavit ought to be read for the Priſoner in caſes of Fellony. It was my Misfortune that Juſtice <hi>Marſhal</hi> Died ſome Days before my Tryal: Who committed this <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah Goodridge,</hi> before whom ſhe inſiſted (as Mr. <hi>Chattleton</hi> who was Clerk to the ſaid Juſtice <hi>Marſhal</hi> can juſtify) that I could neither Read nor Write, which I ſoon contradicted by writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſeveral Languages, ſhe then told the Juſtice ſuch Falſities, that were contradictory in themſelves, which induced Juſtice <hi>Marſhal</hi> to commit her to <hi>New-Priſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <head>Here is a Copy of her Committment.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>Midd. ſſ.</dateline>
                           <salute>Ralph Marſhal</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Receive into your Cuſtody the Body of <hi>Hannah Goodridge</hi> this Day brought before me and charg'd upon the Oath of Capt. <hi>Charles Newey,</hi> for pretending to be his Wife, and on pretence, taking up things in his Name, and contracting Debts, for which he has been Arreſted, whereas ſhe is not his Wife, in breach of her good behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and for refuſing to find ſufficient Sureties for her Perſonal appearance at the next Seſſion of the Peace, to be holden for the ſaid County, her in your Cuſtody ſafely keep until ſhe ſhall find ſufficient Sureties as aforeſaid, or be diſcharged by due courſe of Law:</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given under my Hand and Seal <date>the 5th <hi>Day of</hi> Feb: 1697.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Copia vera Exam per. <hi>William Killvers</hi> Deput Cuſtod ibar</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <trailer>To the Keeper of <hi>New-Priſon</hi> on <hi>Clarken-Well-Green</hi> or his Deputy.</trailer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>I Indicted her, but ſhe got off by ſham Bail, ſo that I never ſaw nor heard of her till of late: I Nonſuited her in the Action ſhe got me Arreſted in, as is recorded in the <hi>Marſhalſea,</hi> and can be certified by Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> of <hi>Cliffords-Inn,</hi> who was my Attorny in that Action, and by his Clerk, whoſe Bill of Charges I now have by me, as well as other Affidavits to this purpoſe, too long to be inſerted here; the Woman that Swore in Court I Cohabited with her Six Weeks in her Houſe, is notoriouſly Forſworn, and found to be one of too black a Character for me to deſcribe; when I asked her whether ſhe was ſure I was the ſame Perſon, ſhe anſwered ſhe did believe I was: And when I asked her, by what Marks ſhe knew me, or whether I wore my own Hair or a Perrywigg, ſhe ſaid ſhe could not tell, it being 4 or 5 Years ſince, ſo might be forgot; Now how eaſy is it for me to prove that at the ſame time ſhe Swore I Cohabited with <hi>Goodridge:</hi> I had the Honour to be in the Family of a Noble Peer of this Relm. And I do not believe that ever his Lordſhip knew or heard that ever I did any thing unworthy of a Gentleman, or believes me Guilty of what's laid to my Charge: My Father was his Lordſhips Tennant, and my Brother Deceas'd Sold his Lordſhip ſometime before his Death, what my Father left, which I ſhould have had ſhare of, as appears by Will, and perhaps is not unknown to his Lordſhip.</p>
            <p>My Wife did not appear in Court, or was there any one that Married her, or ſaw us Married; they brought a Certificate from <hi>Lynn,</hi> that ſuch a Perſon was Married there, whoſe Name was <hi>Ferrour,</hi> and tho' the Indictment was <hi>Ferrow,</hi> yet the Licence was <hi>Ferra,</hi> which might have been three ſeveral Perſons; the Indictment was falſe and therefore they tell me it ought to have been Quaſhed; and that <hi>Hollingworth</hi> ought not to have been made an Evidence for the King, ſeeing he own'd he Forſwore himſelf in <hi>Chancery;</hi> and tho the Court told me, that the Court of <hi>Chancrey</hi> was no Court of Record, (and that I ought to have produced a Record of his being proved Perjured) yet my Lord <hi>Chancelor</hi> ſays it is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Neither indeed ought <hi>Jones</hi> to have been allowed an Evidence againſt me, for tho' an Oath in <hi>Chancery</hi> be no Record againſt <hi>Hollingworth,</hi> yet the <hi>Old-Baily</hi> was one againſt <hi>Jones,</hi> alias <hi>Ambtell,</hi> alias <hi>Clement,</hi> ſeeing it was there Recorded that he own'd himſelf Perjur'd the Seſſions before.</p>
            <p>But the Court ſeemed to Inſiſt moſt upon my having own'd my ſelf Married to ſeveral Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which was never yet allowed of as a proof; For how many Gentlemen have kept Women that have paſſed by their Names, yet was never Married to them: Judge <hi>Nevill</hi> declared laſt Seſſions that he would not for the World believe a Perjur'd Fellow's Evidence againſt any Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner tho' he ſhould ſpeak Truth, and yet I have but Two, upon whoſe ſole Evidence, I was found Guilty, othat are proved Perjured by their own Confeſſions, under the Plauſible pretence (if I may ſo ſpeak) that one did not know what an Oath was; and the other forc'd to it for fear I ſhould Kill him; Why did not the fright he pretends I put him to, make him Committ Murder, Robbery; or rather Swear the Peace againſt me? Was ever Man forc't to Forſware him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in <hi>Chancery;</hi> Can any Mortal be forc't to it, or is there a thing eaſier avoided: Could he find no other pretence for his Perjury: He that commits Murther, excuſes it by ſaying that he was Drunk, and did not know what he did: He that Steals, that it was neceſſity put him upon it: But the Law has no regard to their pretences, or excuſes, or could it therefore ever be the Intention of our wiſe Law-makers, to admit of a Perjur'd Fellows Evidence in caſes of Life, nay in any caſe, when it appeared by any means that they had Forſworn themſelves; for to believe a Villain, or a Perjured Wretch is not at all conſiſtent with Juſtice, or Reaſon; for by ſo doing you'll paſs by the Guilty and deſtroy the Innocent.</p>
            <p>Laws were not made for Enemies, to Revenge themſelves on each other, but to do Juſtice and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109696:7"/>keep Peace, Now that there is ſuch Perſons who out of Malice, Fear, or hopes to get ſomething by the Perſons Death, do Forſweare themſelves, ought not to be doubted, and if too eaſy a beleife be given to thoſe that Swear at Random, what certainty then has any Man for his Life or Eſtate.</p>
            <p>Now that I was, or ever could, be believed to be Married to <hi>Hannah Goodridge,</hi> cannot cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly enter into any unprejudiced Reader's thoughts, there being neither Reaſon nor Luſt, as aforeſaid alledged by my very Enemies, to induce me to it, who had laid one Baſtard to me, and another to another Gentleman; The World cannot but be ſatisfied what a notorious Jilting Whore ſhe ever was, nothing is ſurer than my Committing her to <hi>New-Priſon,</hi> for pretending ſuch a Notion, and contracting Debts in my Name for which I was Arreſted, and ſhe Nonſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not being able to prove her allegations by any, but a moſt notorious wicked Villain; whom my Reader ſees has been proved Perjur'd; therefore ought not to be believed: Moreover if had been Married to her as ſhe pretends, why did ſhe not prove it ſooner: Why did ſhe ſuffer her ſelf to be Nonſuited, and committed to <hi>New-Priſon,</hi> if ſhe was my lawful Wife, why did ſhe hide her ſelf, when ſhe knew I own'd my ſelf Married to another for two Years this <hi>May</hi> But ſhe muſt Proſecute me juſt upon my Siſters Quarrel, who put her on: And tho' my ſaid Siſter Swore before the <hi>Recorder,</hi> as appears by my Committment, yet ſhe declar'd to my Wife and Mrs. <hi>Succy Mair,</hi> as was Sworn in Court, <hi>that ſhe was ſure I never was Married to any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture but to her ſelf, tho' I had lived with other Women,</hi> which my Brother affirmed with Oaths, and with other things to my Praiſe: Now if this pretended Marraige was Celebrated, as was Sworn by this perjured Villain, why was it not Regiſtered in the Church Book, ſeeing there is a Statute that requires it? Why was not the Clark, or ſome Body elſe by, to give her in Marriage? I have asked moſt of <hi>Doctors Commons,</hi> who all tells me it is no Marriage, tho' ſhe produced the Record that was Sworn at the <hi>Old-Baily</hi> againſt me, that tho' ſhe cannot Hang me, yet will ſhe contract Debts, or get ſome Body to pretend to lend her Mony to keep me in Priſon, as ſhe Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins.</p>
            <p>I need not ſay much to convince the World that I never Hung the <hi>Gallows</hi> in Mourning; and that my Siſter is Forſworn in that, at leaſt I hope it will be believed, ſeeing ſhe Swears ſhee's ſure I did it, as appears by my Committment, when the thing it ſelf never was done, nor would the Grand Jury find the Bill, For the People that Live, and has done at <hi>Tyburn</hi> Houſe, for Tenn Year paſt, has been often Examined about it, Nay before the King and Councel; the <hi>Gallows</hi> has been ſearched if any Nay les were driven in, or any of the Mourning appeared there, or there abouts, nothing was ever found or ſeen: The report is ſuppoſed to be occaſioned by the Woman's Father's Death, who now Lives in it, and for whom they were at that time in Mourning.</p>
            <p>That there was never any thing like it ever ſeen, by any of that Family or any other Creature, tho' ſeveral has been charged with it, as the Lord <hi>Mohun</hi> &amp;c. a thing of that nature could not be, without their hearing, ſeeing, or knowing of it, their Houſe being ſo nigh it, and Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows looking towards it; And that it was only a report, is what they are ready to make Oath of before any Judge; I had 3 or 4 to Swear this in Court, leaſt they ſhould find the Bill and Try me upon it Immediately, as they did upon others; but the Court would not hear them.</p>
            <p>I diſcharg'd 5 Recognizances, (before I was Committed) of my Siſters creating, who made her Siſter, her Siſters Husband, her Maid, and others, as ſhe her ſelf did Swear the Peace againſt me; which with her plauſible Railing incenſed the Juſtices, Conſtables, and thoſe that heard her with Tears relate my ſuppoſed Crimes, which Increaſed with her Invention. So that I was look'd upon like a Mad Dog that every one ought to have a throw at, which I am willing to believe occaſion'd Mr. <hi>Turner</hi>'s coming under pretence to aſſiſt the Conſtables, and to a Aſſault me, and then Indite me for Aſſaulting of him, when they told me that the Conſtables were at the Tavern ſtaying for me, I ſent to tell them, that a Conſtable with another might come to me if they pleas'd, for I'd ſuppreſſed what Warrants my Siſter's Malice had procured; They ventured to come to me at laſt; The Conſtable could not Read, but the Beadle did, and ſeem'd ſatisfied with it, that I Reſiſted is certain, tho in my Morning Gown, and to no purpoſe, they being about 40 in Number, but that they Aſſaulted me having no Warrant to break open a Door, is as certain.</p>
            <p>And now I hope my Reader muſt loudly confeſs, that all circumſtances onely conſidered, it will appear to every charitable Judgment, that if I had in the leaſt been conſcientious to my ſelf of having two or more Wives, of Hanging the Gallows in Mourning, of ſuborning a Villain that no Creature could depend upon, unleſs his Swearing was to bring him out of Priſon.</p>
            <p>Muſt I not have been Eſteemed to have totally loſt my Underſtanding, nay to a been a perfect Lunatick, or lull'd into a Lethargie, in not flying from Juſtice, but it behoves us who are Mortals born, to bear with all Afflictions, and to try our Fortunes as often as we are Miſerable, for it is as poſſible to retrieve our former happineſs as to fall from it.</p>
            <p>The Witneſſes againſt me are ſo many Pick-pockets, Cheats, and Villains raked together; <hi>Hollingworth</hi> is known to have been Burnt with the <hi>Flower de luce</hi> upon his Back, and to have been in <hi>New-Priſon</hi> for making of Farthings, one that ſometimes paſſes for a Prieſt, and at others
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109696:7"/>for a Miniſter: I ſaw him abjure the Proteſtant Religion in <hi>Paris,</hi> and take up <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> Orders upon him, but now he pretends himſelf a Proteſtant again. If ſuch Wretches be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, there is nothing either in Heaven or upon Earth, that can be ſecure from them; They are Rogues that will Swear any thing; Fellows known to be Thieves, Cheats, and in fine, a Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal to the very Alms Basket. The Devil's in my Enemies if they do not Win all they play for, when they have the ſhuffling and packing of their Cards, and keeping in, or puting out, as they themſelves pleaſe. The Town will not doubt of my having been purſued with the utmoſt Induſtry and Bitterneſs Imaginable; and that I have had but little Favour ſhewn me, which has left me, but one Fireing Gun to call for help, upon the ſpringing of a Lake.</p>
            <p>So Mortal a Sin is it to aſpire, or ask for ones own, and ſo venial a ſlip to endeavour to take a way any ones Life, with <hi>a non obſtante</hi> of never ſo many Laws to the contrary. My Siſter who will out Swear or out Weep a Harlot, when ſhe vows Fidelity to her old Cully; ſhe is a true expectant Widdow at her old departing Uſures Death Bed-ſide; juſt ſealing her ſole Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutrix. She's particularly marked by continual crying, and inſatiable Malice; for no relenting thought, or pittying Tear, no Love of a Dead and too kind Husband, can be capable to ſtop the Carreer of her unparrallel'd Ingratitude: There never was perhaps ſince the creation, ſo much noiſe made, not only in this vaſt Citty, but in all parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> about a poor young Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, whoſe higheſt Crime was living like a Gentleman; unleſs you'l believe perjured Villains, or thoſe that repeat what the others Swear, or them he diſoblig'd. It's a Siſter in Law (whole Intereſt it is to Laſh me till I fly for Succour to the Grave) that the World ſees I am proſecuted by, and by her mean Scandalous and Ridiculous Inſtruments, Louſie, Greaſie, Rogues, Starv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Indigent Varlets, that have not Credit in the World for a Brumigham Groat, had they been Men of Subſtance, or Reputation, or without Prejudice, by whoſe Teſtimony I had been found Guilty, I had then been ſilenced for ever, in ſome lone Cave dark as deſpair, if I had realy loſt what's dearer then Life, the dreads of which, makes me feel no leſs than all the Pangs of bleeding Death, Racks, and Tortures; In which let me Die, if I am Guilty. My cruel Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies I know will not deny me Dying: But the Witneſſes upon whoſe Oathes I am found Guilty, are now known as well as the Whiping-poſt, for Swearing, Lying, Cheating; and for abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſort of mercenary Villains, who were by my Siſter pitched upon as the rareſt Tooles that ever Ingeneer invented to mannage ſuch a Machine: That Man knows little of my Misfortunes, that knows not what Tricks they play'd to Ruin me.</p>
            <p>The Council for the King, made a motion that they might have leave to lay me open, as they call'd it, which was granted: And who was to lay me open but my Siſter, her Siſter, her Siſter's Husband, and her Maid? For there was not a Creature that ſaid the leaſt thing againſt my Reputation, but her party; Never was there ſuch a motion made by Council, or granted by a C — it ſignifying nothing to the matter of fact, for which I was Indicted. The queſtion being not what I was Born, or what Follies I had been Guilty of, but what Laws I had broke: To prove me no Gentleman Born, my Siſter being upon her Oath, calls for a Creature that to deſcribe, I can only ſay was a Scare crow, whom ſhe declar'd to the Court was my Brother. The whole Court hiſt'd at the ſight of him, He was Sworn and asked by the Court <hi>whether he knew the Priſoner at the Bar, he anſwered yes, very well;</hi> They asked him <hi>how long he had known me,</hi> he ſaid 20 <hi>Years,</hi> And being asked by my Council how Old he was, he ſaid 18 <hi>or</hi> 19, at which the Court Hiſſing, he fell a Crying, and <hi>ſaid they had made him Forſwear himſelf,</hi> and ſo went out of Court.</p>
            <p>If he had been my Brother, had I been the more Guilty of what they charg'd me with, or could I help my being Born a Beggar, ought I not to a been the more eſteem'd for raiſing my ſelf to a Captain, Lievtenant; Is every one capable of it? was there not ſome in Court worſs Born than my ſelf? It's my power to aſpire with art, tho' not to chooſe my part; Let any one think, if I am worth a thought, if I can be Guilty, and they but Examine my Siſter's Tricks and Perjuries, and her Ingratitude by the pains ſhe took and takes, to expoſe her Dead Husband, who had left her all to the prejudice of his two Brothers, to one of which he owed the ſumm in diſpute, with other obligations, which ought never to have been forgotten; to the other Three-ſcore Pounds his Wife having (as can be prov'd) got the Bond for the ſaid ſumm by a Trick into her Hands, and tho' her ſaid Husband was Friends with his Brother when he Died, yet did he leave him, but Five Shillings, tho' he knew he owed him the aforementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Summ.</p>
            <p>Let any one believe if he can, that he was in his Senſes when he made this Will, or that he was not bewitched by his Wives Tears; ſhe that was but a Servant to him; The violence and malice which appeared, and appears, in my Proſecutors, is in it ſelf a certain inſtance of my being wrong'd.</p>
            <p>Poverty is a ſign of honeſty, tho' it ſometimes occaſions Roguery; my want of Birth, Power, Preferment, and Places is thought by the Judicious, to be no more a Diſgrace than that I was not made a Prince, or Invited out of <hi>Newgate</hi> to my Lord <hi>Mayor</hi>'s Feaſt: But he that once falls into his Enemies Power, becomes a Slave, tho' he was free before; Can any Man be ſo eaſily Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109696:8"/>upon, as to Imagin that one who will Forſwear himſelf at one time, will not be brought to do it at another, or when ever he finds it his Intereſt ſo to do? or ought to be believed when he ſpeaks Truth, unleſs in ones own defence: No Rogues ſetts up marks that he may miſs; the World knows and ſees that my caſe is ſingular, not having above one Witneſs to any one mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact: And thoſe prov'd Perjur'd by their own Confeſſions; ſo that I may be Innocent and no affront to thoſe that believ'd me Guilty. At worſt, the ſame Perſons that do great, knows beſt how to Cure them: Vipers and Toads have their extracted Vertues, <hi>Balms</hi> and <hi>Medicines</hi> are drawn from Druggs, and Poiſons, tho' God forbid I ſhould acquieſe with you in my being Guilty: Dead Men can't Bite, neither have they any Friend: Sure any thing that has a Soul, had rather excel others in the knowledge and practice of what is excellent in its kind, than in the extent of power or wickedneſs; all that has been done againſt me, ſeems to be a Dream: For could ſo Inconſiderable a Villain as <hi>Jones</hi> (tho' good at Swearing) undertake ſuch an Enterprize, he could but be Sub-Servient to the deſigne, but an Inſtrument moved by ſome greater ſpring: Sure thoſe that believe, or ſpeak tenderly of Perjury by ſaying that its neceſſary, do it only to excuſe themſelves.</p>
            <p>I beſeech all thoſe that have either known or heard of me, to reſt aſſured notwithſtanding the ſuggeſtions which have been made by my Siſter, and her adherents, who for their own wicked purpoſes, contriv'd ſometimes with Tears, to create a belief in you, that I am the very worſt of Creatures, that nothing is more in my deſires, or ſhall be more my endeavours than retrieving a loſt or blemiſht Reputation, and that you'll reflect upon what ſort of Security any one of you has for your Life; if every Man's Breath lies at the Mercy of a couple of own'd perjur'd Varlets, where is the free born Subjects liberty, when any Creature is made an Evidence for the King, or ſhall be Encouraged in whatever he ſhall ſay, and tho' it be never ſo falſe, yet ſometimes ſhall he not be pryed into by the C— or J—tho' they are Damn'd for believing what he Swears.</p>
            <p>By this that they do it caſt a Covert on one of the Lewdeſt Impieties known by Man: Can Truth arraign the Juſtice of our Nation, whoſe chiefeſt bleſſing is Liberty; or can Perjury be a thing to bleſs God for, or a ſubject to beg a Petition upon, of any real ſervice to a ſociety of Men? To believe perjur'd Wretches, is confounding of Right and Wrong, Good and Evil, and Inverting the very order of Equity, of reward and puniſhment. How many Innocent Men do our Judges implore Mercy for, from the King, whom they find have been Sworn falſly againſt: But how many do they, or may they find not wrong'd. Thoſe that are taken in Robbing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the High-way, have no other way to come off, but turning Evidence; by which they'll ſave their Lives and get Mony to boot: What Innocent Perſon will they not accuſe, to make up the number to clear themſelves: This Seſſions we have one Example; how many Innocent Souls have been clap'd up and kept upon unconſcionable Expence, till all they had left in the World was little enough to pay the Charges of the Priſon: If this be ſuffered, Villany will be Sacred, and to be honeſt, or deſirous to raiſe ones ſelf Hazardous.</p>
            <p>If I am for want of Judgment, thought, or foreſight, miſlead or miſtaken, I hope I may be Pardon'd my not being Infallible. I might, I am afraid, with more eaſe make you believe that the fallen Angels have recovered their primitive Station, and that the glorious Spirits who have ſtood firm ever ſince their Creation, have now joyn'd in a Rebellion againſt their Maker, than to pretend to appear Innocent to all without an Eſtate or Power, in my Whimſical Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. Neither can I Think, Thought, Word, or Deed, Project, Contrivance, or Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which commonly paſs for the proof of things will do it, ſo I appeal to the great God of Heaven and Earth, the Sole Judge of all, and once more in his preſence, I vow that I never had a Thought (tho' ſaid in paſſion) of taking away my Brother or Siſters Life, which if I had, let God of his Mercy now ſtrike me Dead, and never have Pitty of me in this World, or the World to come.</p>
            <p>That if ever I did Engage, ſet on, or promiſe to give 10 Guineas to <hi>Edward Jones,</hi> alias <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brell,</hi> alias <hi>Clement,</hi> to Swear againſt my Siſter <hi>Newey,</hi> may I be Eternally Damn'd: And if I did not lend my Brother Deceas'd, the 105 Guineas in diſpute, in the preſence of <hi>Sarah Laply,</hi> and <hi>John Ball,</hi> and had his Note for them, or may all the Curſes of this World and the other, light upon me; if ever I was Married to <hi>Hannah Goodridge,</hi> by <hi>Hollingworth,</hi> or any other, may the hotteſt Place in Hell be my lot.</p>
            <p>And I do, and will, expect from almighty God, the Vindication of my Integrity and Innocency: Now if a <hi>Lapidary</hi> ſells me at a horrible Price, that which he Warrants for a Ruby of the old Rock, I buy it of him accordingly; if it proves afterwards to be only a Paſt or Dublet, my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie is good againſt him: But where is it againſt my Enemies? what reparation or ſatisfaction can be great enough for what I have wrongfully and unjuſtly ſuffered; without making the Courts of Juſtice Coffee-Houſes, and publick places to ring as loud of their miſtakes, as ever they did of their Invectives.</p>
            <p>To obtain which I would act as the ſweating Chymiſt at his Fire, for Sr. <hi>Humphry Edwin</hi> he ought not for his Siſter's ſake, to have endeavoured ſo hotly, the taking away my Life,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109696:8"/>or Engag'd ſo many of the City to have Ruin'd me, as did, who I dare not Name: Gods connivance at Man's Impiety, may ſometimes be the pollicy of Heaven; were all Crimes puniſhed, Mankind would be deſtroyed, the work of their Creation fall, and the World end too ſoon.</p>
            <p>My Siſter ſent Four of her Neighbours to me, here in the <hi>Preſs-Yard,</hi> with a long Paper for me to Sign; It contained my owning my ſelf Guilty of what had been laid to my charge; if I I would do it, they promiſed me Favour: And Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> told me I ought to do it, ſeeing the Jury had found me Guilty; And that it would be a means for my Siſter to fetch me out, which will not, I ſuppoſe, be denied it being ſo eaſily proved.</p>
            <p>Here is great Clemency indeed, and too great to be good, that my Siſter who had ſo little Mercy, but the other Day, at the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> ſhould now tacitly, and conſequentially pretend to be more Merciful than formerly, but let the Geeſe beware, when the perſecuting Fox be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to Preach; I am afraid, and that not without good Grounds for it too, that this ſudden great conflux of Mercy is not of the right Stamp: I doubt its counterfeit Coyn, and but Caſed over with a pretence of Mercy; I am Jealous that this Mercy of hers, is nothing but Cruelty at the Bottom, and ſelf ended Deſign, ſeeing ſhe would have me acknowledge my ſelf Guilty, but I return'd them for anſwer (being conſcious of my Innocency) that I would rather Starve in Priſon, and Indure the worſt of Deaths, than own ſuch notorious Falſities.</p>
            <p>Now let the World but ſee how knowing ſhe is of her own Guilt, and of my Innocency, or elſe why ſhould ſhe ſend (as the whole Priſon knows, ſhe did) or be ſo troubled in Mind, as not to be able to reſt in her Bed at Nights, for what ſhe fancies ſhe ſees? let not her Imagin that what ſhe has Barbarouſly done againſt me, will be eaſily forgiven her hereafter; tho' it may be no more then making her Siſter, her Siſter's Husband, her Maid, and the poor Boy Forſwear themſelves.</p>
            <p>I cannot ſee if I had been Guilty, which God forbid, of ſuborning this Villain, Marrying two Wives, I ſhould be ſo bad as I am thought. The Villain Swore that I did it only to frighten her to whom my Brother left all, to her who formerly had been his Servant Maid who had not only cheated me by her wheedling Tricks of what I lent; but what elſe belong'd to me, as well as what belong'd to my Brother, who is Living; whom ſhe frightens out of what's his due, and ſearch'd for, after he had hid himſelf, to force him by all ſorts of Threats to Forſwear himſelf againſt me; telling him ſhe would uſe him worſe than ſhe did me; not only in her above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned actings, but in her deſiring I might ſtand in the <hi>Pillory</hi> before her Door: A pretty Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit or reward for her Husband's favours; ſhe that reports I went to take away my Brothers Life, thinking thereby to have every thing believed to my prejudice; endeavours at the ſame time to take away mine, and to force my Brother that's Living to do it, which is what would put a ſtop to my Miſeries. My Brother and Siſter, us'd to value themſelves amongſt their Neighbours, upon their having me for their Brother, till of late, which ſhews to thoſe that have a mind to ſee that all is my Siſters contrivance; I muſt own I have been vain in Living and appearing above what I ought, which with my humour, and ſometimes, owning my ſelf Married to thoſe I never was, created me what Enemies I have; but I thank my Stars, if I have any Stars to thank; that no Creature that rarely knows me, or ever kept me Company, can ſay I ever did any thing unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of a Gentleman, unleſs they'll Eccho what has been invented by my Siſter, or are my Enemies by Inclination, or out of ſome Quarrelſome cauſe. That I never had under any pretence whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of his Execellency Gount <hi>Tallair</hi> 1000 <hi>l.</hi> or a Guinea, is as eaſily proved as it has been Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalouſly reported.</p>
            <p>That I had the Honour to ſerve under him at the Siege of <hi>Reignfield,</hi> and have been Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by him is true; it would have been an eaſy matter for me to a prov'd that it was not in my Nature, or Power to act what was unworthy of what I had acquired by thoſe that have ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with me, or have known me abroad, could they have appeared without any prejudice to themſelves.</p>
            <p>But Crimes like what I am charg'd with, affrightens and aſtoniſhes one's Friends, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents their doing any thing elſe, for one true Friendſhip there is none, or elſe I might have had my ſhare. A Man muſt be very brave indeed, that dares be a Friend in need, or viſit, in a Priſon, on the contrary every Bougher or diſpis'd Coward, dares Triumph over a Dead, or chain'd Lyon.</p>
            <p>My ſuppoſed Robbing upon the High way ought not to be anſwered: Seeing it appears falſe, and that ſuch a thing was only deſired to put an end to my being. And can there be a more convincing Inſtance of my Innocency, than their reporting that I had 18 Wives at once, when they could find but one, and that a Sham one too, deſigned with ſuch Reflections that in what condition ſoever I ſhall be in, I will be above taking Notice of, as I am repining at the decrees of Heaven, which if I did, ſhould but labour wickedly in Vain and ſtruggle with an everlaſting Chain, and after all, be dragg'd along with pain. But to draw to a concluſion.</p>
            <p>Now that I ſhould be thought the worſt of Villains, cryed down by every Mans mouth, for the worſt of Wretches, charg'd and heap'd, with more Crimes than 'tis poſſible for me to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109696:9"/>Guilty of, by any that ever knew me or kept me Compay; ſuppoſe I had been Guilty, which God forbid, yet ought not I to be thought what I am, for what they charge me with, might be the Effects of paſſion, Youth, or Indiſcretion; and being Young ſome hopes was ſtill left for expiation and attonement. But I beg of my Reader by all that's dear to him, that he will but examin what Reaſon or what thing in Nature could be capable to induce me to ſuborn this <hi>Jones,</hi> alias <hi>Ambrell,</hi> alias <hi>Clement,</hi> ſuch a one that my Misfortunes will not permit me to deſcribe, and to take away my Siſter's Life which if accompliſhed, would rather prove my Ruin, and not only the loſs of 105 Guineas lent, but other pretenſions. I wanted no proof I had done my Buſineſs againſt her in <hi>Doctors-Commons,</hi> and at Common-Law, without making uſe of this Fellow; now the World may eaſily know, and ſee that I had no deſign nor could I, if I had been willing which I never was, to take away my Brothers Life which is too falſe an aſperſſion to be bore or believed, that I could be Married to ſuch a one, when there is ſo many better; and not one Reaſon to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce me to this, is what I hope no unprejudiced Perſon will believe, no more than my Hanging the Gallows in Mourning. Can there be in nature a clearer proof of my Innocency, and her barbarous Perjury ſeeing the thing was never done, and that ſhe poſitively Swore that I did it, and had often acknowledg'd it to her. What Impious Inſollence; what Prophain breath, dares or ought, ever to appear in defence of her Wickedneſs and Perjury unleſs they'll dip in her Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety: Can any one believe that ſuch Villains, as the Witneſſes againſt me are known to be, fit Inſtruments to conſumate the finiſhing ſtroak of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>By what I have ſaid I do not nor would I be taken to Arraign the Juſtice of my Country, or the Judges before whom I was Tryed: But yet I muſt beg leave to ſay that I never heard that the Judges or Juries of <hi>England</hi> do or ever did claim to be guided in their proceedings in Caſes of this nature, by any Spirit of Infallibility: For the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> in his pleas of the crown Reports, a ſad Caſe of a Perſons being Condemn'd and Executed, for the Murther of a Girl, who after the Execution of the party ſo condemned, was found to be Living, and in perfect Health; Nay a ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der accident yet happen'd in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Reign, in which 3 Perſons <hi>viz.</hi> the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and her two Sons were Condemn'd, Executed, and Hang'd in Chains, for the Murther of a Perſon who afterwards was found to be Living, and never to be any ways Aſſaulted, or hurt, by thoſe who were Executed for this Murther.</p>
            <p>All this is known to be evidently True: Innocent Perſons you ſee have been Executed by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Verdicts and Judgments, and yet the Judges nor Juries, no ways blemiſhed, but they muſt be taken to proceed always according to what is Sworn, whether True or Falſe, is only what God knows, what has happened may happen again, as is moſt Evident in my Caſe, who am found Guilty on the Evidences of two Villains who are Guilty of Perjury <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a Priſoner be Fin'd more than he is able to Pay, it's the ſame thing as if they Impriſon'd him for Life, which is againſt Law, and what was thought a grievance in the late Reigns, and againſt an Act of Parliament of King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> which ſays no Man ſhall be Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more than he is worth, which is the contents of <hi>Magna Carta,</hi> and worſe then Death, why are there Powers that Barr the Vengeance of ſuch unparallel'd Wrongs as mine, it's my Fate to ſpeake Truth and not to be believ'd, but I am Dumb and ſhall be glad amongſt ſo many <hi>Infidels,</hi> to gain one Believer or make one <hi>Proſelite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is another thing, which I am neither Committed nor Indicted for, I hear has done me as much Harm as what they charge me with, believing my Enemies could do nothing againſt me till the begining of the Seſſions, I neglected what ought to a been done againſt them, to obtain a very Honourable Place, which I certainly had by the Intereſt of ſome Perſons of Quality, had it not been for this Misfortune, which ſtartled my Friends, and was Muſick for my Enemies.</p>
            <p>I ſent to Mr <hi>Gombleton</hi> to borrow a Perriwigg, for mine was gone to be altered, every one knows that I did not want one, it was ſent me, and I was taken with it on, next Morning, he hearing of my Misfortune, came for it, I told him that it had coſt me conſiderable, to come to the <hi>Preſs Yard,</hi> and that they were continually asking me for Mony, and tho' I had Mony owe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, yet could I be ſure of none, being a Priſoner: That I did not know what occaſion I might have, ſo I hoped he would not take it Ill, if I return'd not the Wigg till I had the 10 Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas I had lent him, when he loſt his Mony at the <hi>Beeſſet Bank,</hi> in <hi>Bridges-Street</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> which can be proved by ſeveral Gentlemen, who ſaw me lend him two or three Guineas at a time, as he loſt them: He told me that he was to go to Court that Morning, and that he hoped I would have Patience till his Mony came out of the Countrey; I told him I was rather to be pittied than blamed, that I ſhould not have refuſed him any thing at another time, but in my Circumſtances I queſtioned whether my Debtors would pay me a Farthing of what was owing me.</p>
            <p>He went and brought a <hi>Barber</hi> dreſt like a Gentleman, who Perſonated his Uncle, whom he told me be longed to Court, and ſhould ſerve me, and ſoon get me out, by the Intreſt he had with the Lord <hi>Mayor</hi> and moſt of the City; I told him he could not deny, but that it was a juſt Debt, and that there was a neceſſity for me to borrow Tenn Guineas upon it to pay my ſelf at that time, which I ſhould not have done at another, tho' I had been told that he was a very ill pay Maſter: Then he told me that he believed it was not quite Tenn Guineas, and that he had pay'd
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109696:9"/>a Guinea, or a Half Guinea, to ſuch a Gentleman, beſides what he had paid the Houſe for me, I told him that nothing ſhould induce me to any thing unworthy of a Gentleman, that I would give him a Note under my Hand for what I Receiv'd, and we would account when my Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes were over; He gave me Seven Piſtoles which he ſaid was all he had, or could get; I gave him my Note for the Receit of them before my Wife, who Witneſſed it, and ſaid what he would do to ſerve me.</p>
            <p>But he's known to be a lying Boy which he practiſed at <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> and had like to a been Beaten for it if he had not denied it, Beaten as he was in the Pit at the <hi>Old-Play-Houſe,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Goodard;</hi> he has plaid a Thouſand Tricks in borrowing of Mony, in geting Cloaths given him by paſſing for Mrs. <hi>Weſtcombs</hi> Son, and is ſince gone away without paying his Lodgings, which are things rather to be bluſhed at, than my ſtanding in the <hi>Pillory</hi> upon a perjured Fellows Evidence.</p>
            <p>Can any one blame me for geting my own of a young Fellow, that had no reſidence, I that could not follow him, and had ſo much need of Mony, which is the Sinnews of all affairs, for one cannot be Hanged a Free coſt: I return'd him his Wigg tho' he gave me but Seven Piſtols and is worth 30 <hi>l.</hi> which is a Demonſtration of my acting Civiler than I ought, ſeeing I might have done otherwiſe, but better Men than I, have given way to their Enemies, having been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed by Misfortune or oppreſſed by Multitudes, but he that ſinks under Labour or Affliction, the Opinions or Reproaches of Men are overcome by their own Effeminacy and Softneſs.</p>
            <p>What Noiſe is this that's been made about my ſuppoſed Crimes? cannot our Capital, or our Laws, be ſaved, or a young Man ruin'd without making uſe of perjur'd, Wretches which no one can no more underſtand, than a <hi>Cuckow</hi> the making of a Cabinet, Where will deſign'd, Envy, Malice, and Impudence runn? conſider of it by Common Law which ſays no Man ſhall be Tryed, but by Judges, upon their Oathes; and without prejudice that if his Judges or Jury err againſt him they are puniſhable, and in the Perſon of the King, we'll deny Juſtice to no particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, neither ſhall a Subject be Tryed by perjudic'd Perſons, or Condemned without undoubted, and clear proofs: I hope I ſhall not be blam'd, my being a true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man, and ſpeaking plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> tho' unfortunate, for it never was pretended by any Man, or will it be aſſerted by any Creature, that underſtands himſelf or the conſtitutions of the Government of this Kingdom, that a Subject can or ought to be Buried alive in Priſon, for Miſdeamenor, or Fin'd one more than he is worth; they tell me 'its againſt Common Law, <hi>Magna Carta,</hi> and Thirty Seven Acts of Parliament; No Act of Parliament is allowed binding againſt <hi>Magna Carta,</hi> which is the Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom: I could ſay more to the purpoſe and which could infinitly clear me of all, but I dare not, and therefore ſhall only begg the Town will inform themſelves if my Siſter has not Married for the ſecret Services he did her againſt me, Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> I mean the <hi>Sub-Ordinary</hi> of <hi>Newgate,</hi> or is not to be ſoon Married, and if they find he is Married to her, let them believe me Guilty if they can; eſpecially if they will but Inquire how often the ſaid <hi>Allen</hi> and my Siſter with ſeveral of her Neighbours, was with, and Treated this <hi>Jones</hi> alias <hi>Ambrell,</hi> alias <hi>Clement,</hi> in Diſguiſe in <hi>Newgate;</hi> what means was uſed by them, but eſpicially by this <hi>Allen</hi>'s carrying Letters to the Right Honourable the Lord <hi>Mayor,</hi> Mr. <hi>Recorder</hi> and others, what Tricks he plaid with this <hi>Jones,</hi> to Engage him to Swear againſt me, as well as with all the poor Priſoners by telling them he would ſave their Lives, if they, or their Friends would give what Mony Fate had left them, which when done, he never more appeared: If he did not get Two Guineas of Mr. <hi>Squib</hi> to ſave Mr. <hi>Nortons</hi> Life that Poyſon'd himſelf, or what he wheed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Sr. <hi>George</hi> out of, by telling him what Intereſt he had with the Arch Biſhop; let the World but Inquire of every Priſoner, or Perſon that has had to do with him apart, they'll then no longer wonder at my being found Guilty; I moſt humbly begg the World will but take notice that I have not a Creature that Swears againſt me, or ſaid the leaſt thing againſt my Reputation, but thoſe who own'd themſelves Perjur'd and are of no Credit or Reputation, ſo I may be Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. My Siſter is notoriouſly Forſworn; Firſt in denying her Husbands Hand Writing, or the 105 Guineas being lent tho' ſhe own'd it before: Secondly for Swearing I hung the Gallows in Mourning; when it was never done, this deſerves much more my puniſhment, for making a poor Boy who own'd it in his Fright in the preſence of ſeveral, who are ready to make Affida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit of it, that ſhe had made him Forſwear himſelf againſt me; what Bribes ſhe gives from time to time, to get me Ill us'd in hopes to bring me by Poverty and other Miſeries to own my ſelf Guilty, which I'll rather Die then do, I am in hopes to learn in time, who it was that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to Poyſon me, Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> had not been gone a quarter of an Hour, but I was Invited to Drink hot Ale and Brandy (which is what is Drunk there) and I accepted, but finding it taſt oddly I threw it down, the Dog licking ſome of it up Dyed immediatly, as can be proved by ſeveral, as well as my finding my ſelf Ill and taking counter Poyſon; not that I have any other reaſon in the World to deſire to Live, than that of Clearing my ſelf, which I do aſſure my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhall be the whole ſtudy of my Life; being aſſured that my paſt Indiſcretions cannot but prove a knowing <hi>Pilot</hi> to my future Conduct; And I am ſo far from complaining of my Judges, or Juries that I am ſure they did me juſtice, and can't Act otherwiſe, than according to their Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109696:10"/>I return them my moſt humble thanks, and am troubled at nothing ſo much as at my Paſſion, for which tho' I periſh here, it cannot be too great an Atonement: My not being uſed to be thought Guilty of ſuch Crimes as what they charged me with, and ſeeing the Juſtices be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom I was firſt brought, and my Judges and Juries give Credit to what my Enemies Swore, made me (who had always lived like a Gentleman) Diſtracted, and now renders me (who cannot think of what I am acuſed of, without the greateſt Horror and concern Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) uncapable of Writing as I ſhould, or making my Innocency appear as I ought.</p>
            <p>Tho Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> the Famous <hi>Sub-Ordinary</hi> of <hi>Newgat's</hi> Name being ſet to a Paper lately Printed, and Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled the <hi>Laſt Dying Speech of John Larken,</hi> alias <hi>Young,</hi> be a ſufficent reaſon for the World to ſuſpect the Truth of it, from him who is accuſtomed to make Dying Men, Speak what they never knew or thought of; yet will I leave my Readers to Judge, if I Rail, or ſo much as Mention, the Right Honourable the Lord Chief <hi>Baron,</hi> &amp;c. or how it can be poſſible, <hi>Larken,</hi> ſhould know whether wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he only Copy'd out for me was true or falſe? Whether Copying out any Mans Caſe, can, or ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Trouble a Dying Man? or whether the true ſeaſon was not Mr. <hi>Allens</hi> fear of being Detected, and what he Catch'd at, to prevent his Drowning? Whether it be not a Flaming <hi>Flam-boy,</hi> for the World to ſee his Malice by? An Inſtance of his having Wrong'd me by being an Evidence againſt me: But if he Imagins that ſpeaking Truth or doing what <hi>I</hi> can, to make my <hi>Innocency</hi> appear, be a Crime, its ſuch a one that I deſire to be thought Guilty of, ſeeing <hi>I</hi> Live but for that, its much better to Enquire, when ſuch Monſters, as my Siſter and he, with their Adherents Dyes, then when, or of whom they were Born.</p>
            <p>I have juſt now ſent me from ſuch poor Wretches on the <hi>Common ſide,</hi> (that one would think Invited rather pitty, in Mr. <hi>Allen,</hi> then a deſire of Cheating them) ſeveral Certificates under their own Hands, too long to be incerted all, tho' the Contents of them are confirm'd by almoſt every one, ſome are as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>This is to Certifie, that Dr. <hi>Allen,</hi> Cheated me of Nine Shillings and Six Pence, out of 1 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> ſent me by my Relations.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Witneſs my Hand. <hi>Herbert Herring.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>This is to Certifie, that Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> did Cheat me of Five Shillings, under pretence of being my Friend, when I was Try'd at the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> to ſay I could Read my Neck Verſs, when I could not Read at all, but the ſaid <hi>Allen</hi> kept my Mony and did do me no ſervice.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>The Mark of <hi>John † Fryer.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Captain <hi>Newey,</hi>
                           </salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> has juſt been with Mr. <hi>Barbiſton,</hi> and told him, that he has got you in Priſon for your whole Life, ſo that neither <hi>Barbiſton,</hi> nor <hi>Bennet,</hi> will Certify what they know, for fear.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Yours <hi>Nayle.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Honoured Sr.</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I muſt humbly Beg, you'l excuſe me, till I can get my Liberty, of Certifying under my Hand what Tricks Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> uſed, to perſwade <hi>Jones</hi> when on our ſide, to make himſelf an Evidence againſt you, it's not only what <hi>Jones</hi> told me, but what I my ſelf heard, as did others: Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> is known by the Keepers and every one, to have been very often with <hi>Jones,</hi> alone in the <hi>Cellar,</hi> when ſeveral of us asked <hi>Jones</hi> why he would Swear againſt you: He ſaid if he did not do it others would, and that you were a Dead Man, and that he muſt do it, or he was ruined for ever. When I am out, I will make Affidavit of what I know; but I believe Captain <hi>Heart,</hi> who is Mr. <hi>Allens</hi> Countrey Man, can do you a great deal of good, only he's afraid: He has often ſaid you were the moſt wrong'd of any one Living.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Yours</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> had Two Shillings given him in preſence of ſeveral, by a Gentleman to give ſuch poor Priſoners, who were Periſhing on the <hi>Common ſide;</hi> he not knowing who were objects of Charity: Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> diſpoſed of one of them, amongſt Three or Four, but kept the other, and Drunk it at the <hi>Bar;</hi> this can be Certified by Fifty: The World ſees, all the Witneſſes againſt me, are of Scandalous Lives, and Converſations, <hi>Jones</hi> own'd himſelf Perjured, <hi>Hollingworth</hi> own'd it likewiſe, and Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> the promoter we find of a clear Character, but ſomething like <hi>Jones,</hi> who he top'd upon me, and pretended to have Converted, as the ſaid <hi>Allen</hi> Swore at my Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. But why ought I to vallue (at this rate) what the <hi>Mobb,</hi> or they ſay, or think of me, whoſe Manners, and Language ſmell ſo Intirely of their Crimes and Vices; its not that ſort I'd Pleaſe, or be thought well of by, but <hi>Si de me Cato ſi Lelius ſapiens ſi allter, Cato ſi duo ſcipiones iſta Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querentur.</hi> If a Man of Merit, or Goodneſs of his own knowledge, ſhould Report theſe things of me, I'd then reaſon to be Afflicted; but they are thoſe who have loſt their Honours, and Conſciences: They that Reproaches us with any thing we are not Guilty of, tells us we ought to Afflict our ſelves no more, then if they told us we were Sick when we were well; the Diſtance is not great from Evil to Good; and there is in every Man a Thouſand Imprefections, which Ballances, what he has that is Good: So Men ought not to Triumph at the rate they do, over the Miſerable or Unfortunate, but bleſs God they are not Worſe, and Conclude that what Merit ſoever they have; what Favours ſo ever Fortune does them; what high Rank ſoever they ſee themſelves Raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to by their Birth, or Exploits, that they are not ſure of Preſerving themſelves, or what they have one poor Month: I ſhall Conclude having (I am afraid) Tranſgreſſed, by ſaying no Mortal has been more Wrong'd, and Imploring the World to reſt aſſured, that nothing ſhall ever be omitted by me, to make my Innocency appear, or retrive what's Blackn'd; being not in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality what I am Repreſented; but Unfortunate.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Newey.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:109696:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
